Inventory of the Richard T. Davies Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Richard T. Davies Papers
1952-2004
2006C16
Davies, Richard T. (Richard Townsend), 1920-2005.
17 manuscript boxes 6.8 linear feet
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, interview transcripts, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to American foreign policy and especially to relations between the United States and Poland.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research. Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives Audiovisual Specialist for further information.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2005.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biography / Administrative History
Richard T. Davies was U.S. ambassador to Poland from 1973 to 1978. Davies, who joined the Foreign Service in 1947, spent his first two years in Poland as a consular and political officer at the U.S. Embassy in Warsaw. His later assignments included counselor for political affairs at the U.S. Embassy in Moscow during the Cuban missile crisis in 1962, director of the U.S. Information Agency for the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, and deputy assistant secretary of state for European affairs from 1970 to 1972.
During his five years as ambassador to Poland, Davies worked on trade issues and helped arrange state visits by Presidents Gerald Ford and Jimmy Carter. He also met frequently with members of the nascent democratic opposition movement against the communist-led Polish government, as well as with Catholic cardinals Stefan Wyszynski and Karol Wojtyla. The special relationship with Cardinal Wojtyla of Cracow, the future pope John Paul II, that Ambassador Davies helped establish turned out to be particularly valuable for the United States in the waning years of the cold war, during President Reagan's showdown with the Soviets. Ambassador Davies's tenure in Warsaw also coincided with a successful penetration of Soviet defenses by U.S. intelligence, the result of the services rendered the United States, the West, and NATO by Colonel Ryszard Kuklinski, who during 1972-81 turned over to the Central Intelligence Agency some 30,000 Soviet documents containing the plans of the Warsaw Pact for the invasion of Western Europe and, in 1980-1981, its plans for the invasion of Poland to suppress Solidarity. Richard Davies retired as director of the State Department's human intelligence office in Washington in 1980.
After retirement, Ambassador Davies chaired the Solidarity Endowment, a U.S. group supporting the Polish workers' movement. From 1990 to 1998, he participated in Partners for Democratic Change, an international organization founded to foster civil societies and institutions in Central and Eastern Europe. He also contributed frequently to op-ed pages. Davies died in Washington in 2005.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Richard T. Davies Papers contain speeches and writings, interview transcripts, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to American foreign policy and especially to relations between the United States and Poland.
Included among the papers is an extensive transcript of an oral history interview that covers Davies' entire Foreign Service career. The papers also document Colonel Ryszard Kuklinski's achievements and Davies' efforts to assist him after his escape to the United States. Kuklinski turned thousands of critical Soviet documents over to the Central Intelligence Agency.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
United States--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; United States--Foreign relations--1989-; United States. Dept. of State.
Occupations
Diplomats--United States.
Container List
- General, 1952-1996
  - 1952/1980 (Box 1)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - 1983-1985 (Box 3)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 4)
  - 1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - 1994-1996 (Box 7)
- Back to the Future Seminars (Box 8)
- Oral history transcripts, 1947-1980 (Box 8)
- Kuklinski, Ryszard (Box 9-10)
- Religion in Communist Dominated Areas, 1982-1992
  - 1982-1987 (Box 11)
  - 1988-1992 (Box 12)
- Subject File
  - Cold war (Box 13)
  - Cuban missile crisis (Box 13)
  - Ethics in government seminar (Box 13)
  - Evergreen Society, 1980-1991 (Box 13)
  - Galanskov, case of (Box 13)
  - Gore, Albert (Box 14)
  - Kronstadt thesis (Box 14)
  - NATO expansion (Box 14)
  - Polish crisis, 1980-1982 (Box 15)
  - Solidarity (Box 15)
  - Soviet Jewish emigration (Box 15)
  - State and party (Box 16)
  - Warsaw, 1977-1978 (Box 16)
  - Photographs (Box 16)
  - Reviews (Box 17)
  - Speeches (Box 17)